Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.15
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Under-Secretary-General of the United Nations, 1992-1993; XV.
  - Events and Schedules, 5.
    - Weekly Schedules, March, 1992-February, 1993 (Box 971, Folder 41)
    - Invitation Acceptances, March, 1992-January, 1993 (Box 971, Folder 42-52)
  - Foreign Trips, 6.
    In the course of carrying out his responsibilities, Thornburgh made four foreign trips during his year at the United Nations. His trip to Moscow, Russia, was mostly "money-related," since Russia was $400 million in arrears to the organization. During this trip, consequently, Thornburgh urged Russian officials to re-pay these debts. Talks were cordial, yet still, Thornburgh writes, produced a commitment no stronger than "'we will do our best' " (Evidence, p. 326).
    His visit to Ethiopia and Kenya was strongly related to wasteful spending, and officials' responses, Thornburgh says, were no more encouraging. "When I asked program managers [in Ethiopia] for a progress report, they responded with an hour's whining about inadequate resources" (Evidence, p.327). The UN's Economic Commission for Africa, stationed in Ethiopia, was suspected of fraud and abuse. Thornburgh also had to handle Kenya's requests for financial aid, which were largely dependant on Kenya's initiatives to reform their political system and deal with national security.
    Thornburgh's travels also took him to Vienna, Austria-home of the UN's Industrial Development Organization (UNIDO) and offices on disability, drugs and crime-and Geneva, Switzerland-home of the World Health Organization (WHO), European Economic Commission, the office of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), and the UN Conference on Trade and Development (UNCTAD).
    Thornburgh's travels to Rome to attend the Vatican Conference on Religion and Disability, represented an area of long-standing interest which Thornburgh admits was not part of his official portfolio. However, Thornburgh had pledged that the UN would seek to advance the rights of people with disabilities. Ginny Thornburgh, who accompanied him to Rome, had invested a major amount of time and effort into making the conference a success. Thornburgh recalls that her moving speech was interrupted several times by applause and that she received a standing ovation at its end (Evidence, p.328). These events also related to the UN General Assembly's conference and meetings (held in Montreal, Canada) marking the end of the UN's Decade for the Disabled in October 1992.
    The information in the UN trip files is divided into "pre-trip," "trip material," and "post trip" background, schedules and related materials. The trips are arranged as follows: 1) Trip to Geneva, Switzerland, and Vienna, Austria, March 18-21, 1992; 2) Administrative Committee on Coordination of the World Health Organization (WHO) meetings, Geneva, Switzerland, April 7-13, 1992; 3) Trip to Addis Ababa, Ethiopia and Nairobi, Kenya (UN Environment Programme and UN Center for Human Settlements), August 4-11, 1992; and 4) Thornburgh and Ginny's trip to Moscow and Rome (the Vatican Pontifical Council International Conference, "Disabled Persons and Society"), November 17-22, 1992.
    - Trip to Geneva, Switzerland and Vienna, Austria
      - Trip material: welcome book on Vienna, March 18-21, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 1)
      - Trip material: Briefing binder on United Nations (UN) issues and trip meeting material, March 18-21, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 2)
      - Trip material: Trip itinerary, March 18-21, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 3)
      - Trip material: Official notes of Secretary General's meeting with the permanent representative of Austria, March 18-21, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 4)
      - Trip material: Dick Thornburgh's notes on issues and meetings, includes trip itineraries, March 18-21, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 5)
      - Trip material: Briefing materials on the Division of Administrative and Common Services (DACS), March 18-21, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 6)
      - Post-trip material: Monthly report of administrative activities at United Nations Office at Vienna (UNOV), and summary of issues relating to the UN office at Vienna, March 18-21, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 7)
      - Post-trip material: Monthly report of administrative activities at United Nations Office at Vienna (UNOV), and Armando Duque's comments on the Ruedas report, March 18-21, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 8)
    - Administrative Committee on Coordination of the WHO Meetings and the Eastern European Conference on Disabilities, Geneva, Switzerland, Prague, Czeck and Slovak Federal Republic
      - Pre-trip material: Notes on items on the meeting agenda of the UN Directors of the Geneva group, regarding good and bad administrative and financial practice, April 7-13, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 9)
      - Trip material: Guidebooks, maps, and luncheon invitations, April 7-13, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 10)
      - Trip material: Briefing binder for trip, April 7-13, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 11)
      - Trip material: Meeting agendas and issues, including Thornburgh's notes, April 7-13, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 12)
      - Trip material: Media reports of Thornburgh's work in Czech, Prague and Slovak Republic, April 7-13, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 13)
      - Trip material: Remarks by Thornburgh to the Opening Session of the Eastern European Conference on Disabilities, Prague, Czech and Slovak Federal Republic, April 7-13, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 14)
    - Trip to Addis Ababa, Ethiopia and Nairobi, Kenya (UN Environment Programme and UN Center for Human Settlements)
      - Pre-trip material: Travel arrangements, including itineraries, phone contact lists, airplane tickets, requests for meeting rescheduling, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 15)
      - Pre-trip material: Letter from UN Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali to Meles Zenawi, president of the Transitional Government of Ethiopia, regarding Thornburgh's visit, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 16)
      - Pre-trip material: Letter from UN Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali to Daniel Toroitich arap Moi, president of the Republic of Kenya, regarding Thornburgh's visit, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 17)
      - Pre-trip material: Newspaper articles on Ethiopia, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 18)
      - Pre-trip material: Newspaper articles on Kenya, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 19)
      - Pre-trip material: Statements made by Thornburgh to the Staff/Management Coordinating Committee (SMCC), sent to the UN Economic Commission for Africa, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 20)
      - Pre-trip material: Thornburgh's talking points and information on the Economic Commission of Africa (ECA) for meetings with the Ethiopia Foreign Minister, H.E. Seyoum Mesfin, and Ethiopia President Meles Zenawi, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 21)
      - Trip material: Greetings and luncheon invitations from Ethiopia, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 22)
      - Trip material: Memorabilia and luncheon invitations from Kenya, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 23)
      - Trip material: Trip itinerary for Ethiopia visit, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 24)
      - Trip material: Trip itinerary for Kenya visit, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 972, Folder 25)
      - Trip material: Briefing material for Ethiopia visit, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 1)
      - Trip material: Briefing material for Kenya visit, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 2)
      - Trip material: Briefing materials on meeting regarding Kenya security incidents, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 3)
      - Trip material: News articles on Kenya (and greater Africa), August 4-11, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 4)
      - Trip material: Briefing materials on the GRID Programme (Global Resources Information Database), Kenya refugees, and proposed property rental increases in Kenya, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 5)
      - Trip material: Thornburgh's notes, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 6)
      - Trip material: Thornburgh's notes on Kenya with references to USIA trip made during Thornburgh's governorship (July 19-August 4, 1986), August 4-11, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 7)
      - Trip material: "In and Out of Africa, Part II," Thornburgh's trip diary, includes drafts and final copy, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 8)
      - Post-trip material: Thornburgh's report to the Secretary-General on his trip to Africa, August 4-11, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 9)
    - Dick and Ginny Thornburgh's trip to Moscow, Russia and Rome, Italy (the Vatican Pontifical Council International Conference, "Disabled Persons and Society")
      - Pre-trip material: Travel arrangements, including schedules, meetings, airplane tickets, and correspondence, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 10)
      - Pre-trip material: Trip itineraries and scheduling, including briefing on crime and safety, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 11)
      - Pre-trip material: Briefing material on the Vatican Pontifical Council International Conference, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 12)
      - Pre-trip material: Thornburgh's preparatory materials for presentation to the Vatican Conference, including notes and past speeches given by Thornburgh, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 13)
      - Pre-trip material: Briefing material on disability laws in different parts of the world, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 14)
      - Pre-trip material: Neil Pike Institute for the Handicapped, briefing materials regarding persons with disabilities, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 973, Folder 15)
      - Pre-trip material: Briefing material on the UN's involvement in disabilities, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 1)
      - Pre-trip material: Informational booklet on the UN General Assembly's "Decade of Disabled Persons" conference in Montreal, Canada (October 8-9, 1992), November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 2)
      - Pre-trip material: Participant folder for the International Conference on Ministers Responsible for the Status of Persons with Disabilities, Montreal, Canada (October 8-9, 1992), November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 3)
      - Pre-trip material: Briefing materials for the International Conference on Ministers Responsible for the Status of Persons with Disabilities, includes statement by Dick Thornburgh, Montreal, Canada (October 8-9, 1992), November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 4)
      - Pre-trip material: Brochures and publications on disabilities published by the United Nations and the National Organization on Disability, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 5)
      - Pre-trip material: National Disability Center, invitation for Ginny Thornburgh to be a board member, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 6)
      - Pre-trip material: Newspaper articles regarding Moscow, Russia, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 7)
      - Trip material: Briefing binder for Moscow and Rome visit, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 8)
      - Trip material: Briefing material on the Russian press, ethnic and territorial disputes in Russia, and Russia political activity, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 9)
      - Trip material: Trip itinerary for Moscow visit, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 10)
      - Trip material: Booklets and articles regarding Russia, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 11)
      - Trip material: Dinners and luncheon invitations for Rome visit, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 12)
      - Trip material: "The Disabled and the Law Throughout the World," An address by Dick Thornburgh to the Seventh International Conference of the Pontifical Council for Pastoral Assistance to Health Care Workers, The Vatican, Rome, Italy, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 13)
      - Trip material: Thornburgh's notes on trip and meetings, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 14)
      - Trip material: Trip diary of Russia and Italy trips (includes notes and drafts), November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 15)
      - Post-trip material: Thornburgh's report to the Secretary-General, Director of the Information Center Division of the Department of Public Information, on his trip to Moscow and Rome, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 16)
      - Post-trip material: UN initiatives and involvement in disabilities and resources for disabled persons, November 17-22, 1992 (Box 974, Folder 17)
  - News Clippings and UN Publications, 7.
    This section contains all major newspaper and magazine articles and major UN publications from the year that Thornburgh worked in the UN. There are also newspaper clippings about the UN that Thornburgh accumulated before his work there, beginning in 1992.
    There are two sections: newspaper clippings and UN publications.
    - News Clippings
      - UN articles and news clippings, 1989-1992 (Box 975, Folder 1-2)
      - Clippings about Thornburgh, March, 1992-March, 1993 (Box 975, Folder 3)
      - UN issues and actions, February, 1992-March, 1993 (Box 975, Folder 4-5)
    - UN Publications
      - "UN in Transition," Development Forum, Vol. 20, No. 5, September-October, 1992 (Box 975, Folder 6)
      - Diplomatic World Bulletin, February 17, 1992-March 22, 1992 (Box 975, Folder 7-8)
      - UN Staff Report, April, 1992-March, 1993 (Box 975, Folder 9)
      - Secretariat News, 1992 (Box 975, Folder 10)
      - Spotlight, UN Review, BCUN Briefing (Thornburgh Interview), and OPC Bulletin, October, 1992-February, 1993 (Box 975, Folder 11)
  - Country Files, 8.
    The United Nations "country files" contain two distinct types of materials. The first relates to briefing and background material on representatives and officials from different member countries of the UN. The second group consists of background information and material on the member countries themselves, arranged alphabetically by country name.
    - UN news releases regarding country representatives, 1988-1992 (Box 976, Folder 1)
    - Appointees from different countries, 1982-1992 (Box 976, Folder 2)
    - Country recruitment updates and talking points, September, 1992 (Box 976, Folder 3)
    - "Top echelon" from different countries, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 4)
    - Australia, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 5)
    - Austria, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 6)
    - Belgium, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 7)
    - Bulgaria, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 8)
    - Burkina Faso, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 9)
    - Cambodia, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 10)
    - Canada, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 11)
    - Chile, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 12)
    - China, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 13)
    - Congo, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 14)
    - Cyprus, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 15)
    - Denmark, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 16)
    - El Salvador, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 17)
    - Ethiopia, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 18)
    - Finland, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 19)
    - France, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 20)
    - Germany, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 21)
    - Iceland, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 22)
    - India, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 23)
    - Indonesia, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 24)
    - Iraq, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 25)
    - Ireland, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 26)
    - Israel, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 27)
    - Italy, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 28)
    - Japan, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 29)
    - Kenya, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 30)
    - Korea, Republic of (South Korea), 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 31)
    - Korea, Democratic Republic of (North Korea), 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 32)
    - Luxembourg, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 33)
    - Netherlands, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 34)
    - New Zealand, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 35)
    - Nigeria, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 36)
    - Norway, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 37)
    - Pakistan, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 38)
    - Panama, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 39)
    - Poland, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 40)
    - Portugal, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 41)
    - Romania, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 42)
    - Russia, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 43)
    - Singapore, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 44)
    - South Africa, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 45)
    - Spain, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 46)
    - Sweden, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 47)
    - Switzerland, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 48)
    - Thailand, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 49)
    - Tunisia, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 50)
    - Turkey, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 51)
    - Ukraine, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 52)
    - United Kingdom (UK), 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 53)
    - United States of America (U.S.), 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 54)
    - Western Sahara, 1992-1993 (Box 976, Folder 55)
  - Ongoing United Nations Material, 1993-2000; 9.
    As originally scheduled, Thornburgh's year at the UN ended in February 1993, after presenting his cumulative report and assessment of the organization's financial situation. His recommendations for reform in his final report, later known as the "Thornburgh Report," were thoughtfully examined and in part enacted over time. Two years after Thornburgh's departure from the UN, the National Journal wrote about his work there, "'The impetus for administrative and fiscal reforms at the United Nations can be credited in large part to intense prodding during the Reagan and Bush administrations. Many of today's cost-cutting stratagems, including the creation of a quasi-inspector general's post to ferret out fraud and waste, stem from a management review conducted by President Bush's Attorney General Dick Thornburgh'" (Evidence, 332).
    Dick Thornburgh has maintained his interest in the activities of the UN and efforts to restructure and reform its finances, prompting letters of thanks from Secretary-General Kofi Annan, and a wealth of ongoing material relating to the UN, its branches, and members. This group of files reflects Thornburgh's continuing interest in the future of the UN and its ability to efficiently meet the needs of its global constituents, and is maintained here in chronological order. It must be noted that the dates of this material follow those of his time there (1992-1993) and continue up to and including 2000.
    The files include, for example: correspondence, testimony, task force reports, news clippings, concept papers, news releases, and speeches.
    - United States Mission to the United Nations: news releases and addresses by Madeline Albright and President George Bush (from 1989), 1989-1993 (Box 976, Folder 56)
    - "Concept paper: Restructuring UN Economic and Social Programmes" and "Strengthening the UN and Enhancing War Prevention: A Grant Proposal", October, 1992-June, 1993 (Box 976, Folder 57)
    - Foreign Policy Research Institute: newsletter, Wire, March-June, 1993 (Box 976, Folder 58)
    - UN publications: Diplomatic World Bulletin, May-June, 1993 (Box 977, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings regarding UN, May-September, 1993 (Box 977, Folder 2)
    - UN publications: Secretariat News, July, 1993-May, 1994 (Box 977, Folder 3)
    - "Accountability and Oversight of the UN Secretariat," draft of report by the UN Joint Inspection Unit Report, August 16, 1993 (Box 977, Folder 4)
    - Commission on Global Governance: members, issues and terms of reference, September, 1993 (Box 977, Folder 5)
    - "Defining Purpose: The United Nations and the Health of Nations," final report by the United States Commission on Improving the Effectiveness of the United Nations, September, 1993 (Box 977, Folder 6)
    - "Response to Request for Proposals for Legal Advisors for the Custody Project," a proposal for the UN Joint Pension Fund by Kirkpatrick & Lockhart (K&L), October 28, 1993 (Box 977, Folder 7)
    - "We're Not Bananas!: The Concept of 'People' in the Principle of Self-determination and its Implications for the UN," report by Harris O. Schoenberg, 1993 (Box 977, Folder 8)
    - News clippings regarding UN, 1993 (Box 977, Folder 9)
    - Emergency Coalition for U.S. Financial Support of the United Nations: background, 1993, 1997 (Box 977, Folder 10)
    - Office of the Inspector General issue at the UN, 1993-1994 (Box 977, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence to Thornburgh regarding the UN, 1993-1997 (Box 977, Folder 12)
    - Business Council for the UN: newsletters, annual reports and correspondence, 1993-1998 (Box 977, Folder 13)
    - UN Association of America: brochures and publications, including material regarding UN financing, 1993-1999 (Box 977, Folder 14)
    - UN related events, regretted by Thornburgh, 1993-2000 (Box 978, Folder 1)
    - UN publications: UN Staff Report, January-April, 1994 (Box 978, Folder 2)
    - Carnegie Corporation of New York: news releases and publications, July-September, 1994 (Box 978, Folder 3)
    - News clippings regarding UN, 1994 (Box 978, Folder 4)
    - U.S. Department of State: letter from Douglas Bennet and action memoranda regarding making the UN a more effective instrument for serving global interests, 1994-1995 (Box 978, Folder 5)
    - United Nations Development Programme (UNDP): publications and reports, 1994-1997 (Box 978, Folder 6)
    - Outline of Thornburgh's testimony to the U.S. House of Representatives Subcommittee on Commerce, State and Judiciary: includes preparatory materials and Thornburgh's copy of his final report to the Secretary-General (SG), dated March 1, 1993, January 25, 1995 (Box 978, Folder 7)
    - Testimony of John R. Bolton before the U.S. House of Representatives Subcommittee on Commerce, State and Judiciary, January 25, 1995 (Box 978, Folder 8)
    - Pittsburgh UN50 Coalition: correspondence, April-December, 1995 (Box 978, Folder 9)
    - Joseph Connor, Under-Secretary-General (USG) for Administration and Management with enclosures regarding financing and efficiency problems at the UN, September 26, 1995 (Box 978, Folder 10)
    - News clippings regarding UN, 1995 (Box 978, Folder 11)
    - "A Call to Action: Summary of Our Global Neighborhood," the report of the Commission on Global Governance, 1995 (Box 978, Folder 12)
    - Council on Foreign Relations: "American National Interest and the United Nations: Statement and Report of an Independent Task Force", 1995-1996 (Box 978, Folder 13)
    - News clippings urging the appointment of Dick Thornburgh as Secretary-General (SG) of the UN, editorials in the Greensburg Tribune-Review, December 8, 1996 (Box 978, Folder 14)
    - News clippings regarding UN, 1996 (Box 978, Folder 15)
    - Letter to Thornburgh from Kofi Annan regarding Thornburgh's final report to the Secretary-General and the financial situation of the UN, January 7, 1997 (Box 978, Folder 16)
    - American Enterprise Institute: letter from Thornburgh to John Bolton regarding his new position as senior vice president, January, 1997 (Box 978, Folder 17)
    - News clippings regarding UN, 1997 (Box 978, Folder 18)
    - Thornburgh's correspondence to and from and about Kofi Annan, and other related material, 1997-1998 (Box 978, Folder 19)
    - News clippings regarding UN, 1998-2000 (Box 978, Folder 20)